CURRICULUM VITAE

MANDERE ORANGI WILFRED P.O Box 150-40506, Kebirigo. Phone: 0700370832/0736553117

Email: wmande.2007@gmail.com

PERSONAL DETAILS

Date of Birth: 23rd April, 1986. Id No: 27629323 Gender: Male Nationality: Kenyan

OVERALL CAREER OBJECTIVE

To work in a dynamic and growth oriented institution, seize available opportunities for professional growth to facilitate realization of corporate goals and as well as enhance self-actualization by consistently applying the knowledge and skills I have acquired through my 4 years' experience as a QA professional and interact with other professionals as well as pursue new skills in order to optimize my competence in the quality management field.

PERSONAL PROFILE

I am a highly determined, self-driven and result oriented professional, with a deep sense of responsibility and accountability. I embrace teamwork and I have formidable communication as well as interpersonal relation skills. I have acquired vast analytical and problem solving skills during my 4 year interaction with manufacturing processes involving production of Aluminium cookware, checkered plates, Aluminium and steel based roofing systems. I strongly believe in a continuous improvement culture and aspire to grow even better.

KEY ABILITIES

ICT Skills: Great proficiency in working with Microsoft Office Applications, Computing and

Designing as well as use of Internet.

Communication Skills: Fluent spoken and written English and Swahili Languages.

Resourcefulness: Critical thinker, innovative, result oriented, relates well with others and seeks

insights into challenges at hand.

Leadership: A good leader in both strategic thinking, communication and project management.

ACADEMIC QUALIFICATIONS

2009-2013: Kenyatta University (main campus).

Pursued a Degree in BSC. Analytical Chemistry with Management.

Jan - March, 2008: Dakmo Computer College.

Studied MS Widows, MS-Word, Excel spreadsheets, Powerpoint, Publisher and adobe PageMaker, Internet and Web Design.

2003-2007: Enkinda S.D.A Mixed Secondary School;

2007: Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education. Attained A-

2006: Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education. Attained B+

1994 - 2003: Maagonga D.E.B Primary School;

Kenya Certificate of Primary Education. Attained 359 Marks.

RESPONSIBILITIES AND ACHIEVEMENTS

- 2012 2013: I served as Chairperson of Kenyatta University Green Chemistry Club (KUGCC). Steered the development of better methods of waste management by separating biodegradable, non-biodegradable and recyclables for efficient waste disposal management at Kenyatta University.
- **2011 2011**: Served as a representative of the School of Pure and Applied Sciences (chemistry department)) in the Kenyatta University Quality Assurance Team.
- Jan Nov 2011: Served in the Human Resource Management docket for High School Science and Technology Empowerment Programme (HSTEP) - KU CHAPTER, a club founded by Science and Technology Students with the objective of mentoring and nurturing young scientists in both the university and high schools.

Major roles included; facilitation of new member recruitment and orientation, organized capacity building programmes and ensured general welfare of all participants.

2010 - 2011: Served as the Organizing Secretary of the Kenyatta University Society of Industrial and Analytical Chemists (KUSIAC).

Main roles included:

Organizing club events (seminars, community service, sports, picnics and meetings), made payments on behalf of the club in liaison with the Finance Secretary, and ensured regular and timely communication to all members.

- **2009 2010**: Served as the class representative of Analytical chemistry students, 2009 group.
- **2009 2012**: Active member of Kenyatta University Entrepreneurship Club and the Red Cross Society.
- **2006 2007:** I served as school captain at Enkinda Secondary.

WORK EXPERIENCE

May 2019 - Present: Space and Style Ltd, Kenya.

- Acting Head of Factory Operations.

- Formulate business strategy with others in the executive team. Assist in development of strategic plans for operational activity. Implement and manage operational plans.
- Design policies that align with overall strategy.
- Implement efficient processes and standards.
- Coordinate customer service operations and find ways to ensure customer retention.
- Ensure compliance with local and international laws (e.g. data protection).
- Oversee the implementation of technology solutions throughout the organization.
- Manage contracts and relations with customers, vendors, partners and other stakeholders.
- Utilize financial data to improve on cost reduction objectives.
- Improve processes and support of organizational goals. Formulate and implement departmental and organizational procedures to maximize output.
- Evaluate risk and lead quality assurance efforts.
- Oversee expenses and budgeting to help the organization optimize costs and benefits.
- Liaise with procurement team to determine and avail raw materials and other requirements.
- Mentor and motivate teams to achieve productivity and engagement.

- Report on operational performance and suggest improvements.
- Directing quality objectives to maximize profitability.
- Co-ordinate and monitor the work of various sub departments involved in production, warehousing and dispatch of goods.
- Manage quality and quantity of employee output and maintenance of equipment and machinery and provide technical support where necessary.
- Monitor performance and implement improvements ensuring quality of products.
- Any other duty as assigned by Management.

Oct 2018 – Present: Space and Style Ltd, Kenya.

- Quality Assurance Supervisor.

- Determining, negotiating and agreeing on in-house quality procedures, standards and specifications.
- Assessing customer requirements and ensuring that these are met.
- Maintaining safe and clean work environment by educating and directing personnel on the use of all control points, equipment and resources.
- Specifying quality requirements of raw materials with suppliers and external providers.
- Investigating and setting standards for quality, health and safety.
- Ensuring that production and quality processes comply with both national and international standards.
- Working with production and quality assurance staff to establish procedures, standards and systems.
- Preparing daily quality and analysis reports and ensuring that all the records are up to date.
- Organizing and coordinating QMS, EMS and OSHA internal audits, informing management reviews and actioning improvement points.
- Training the team on Kaizen, ISO Standards and best practice to optimize performance.
- Acting as a catalyst for change and improvement in performance and quality.
- Directing quality objectives to maximize profitability. Any other duty as assigned by Management.

June 2014 - Sep 2018: Kaluworks Ltd, Kenya.

- Quality Assurance Engineer.

- Developing and continually improving the Quality Management System through establishment of SOPs, re-validation of standards, overseeing stringent QC checks (on raw materials, process and FG inspection) to guarantee full product conformity to customer requirements and other applicable compliance requirements, ensuring customer satisfaction.
- Promoting Continuous Business Improvement.
- Actively facilitating internal QMS & EMS audits, conducting ISO transition/upgradation awareness trainings, Promoting Kaizen, team-work, health safety & facilitating development of new QC staff.
- Attending and presenting daily QC reports in daily management meetings.
- Preparing and presenting monthly QC performance presentations in production-engineering and management review meetings.
- Attending and resolving Customer Complaints, conducting root cause analysis & corrective action planning.
- Monitoring and controlling QA related consumables and other resources.
- Facilitating evaluation and re-evaluation of Suppliers and other external providers.

2013-2014: CORRUGATED SHEETS LIMITED, Pickling Division

- Operations & Quality Control Incharge Acid Regeneration Plant (ARP)
 - Ensured smooth plant operations, good quality RGA production, identified machine maintenance needs and coordinated all maintenance activities (preventive, breakdown & scheduled maintenance).
 - Enforced thorough house-keeping standards, health safety, and consistent record keeping & reporting as well as conducted new staff inductions & intern training.

MAY – AUG, 2012: KENYA ELECTRICITY GENERATION COMPANY LIMITED.

-Analytical Chemist (attachee) at KenGen, Olkaria Geothermal Project.

- Gained hands-on skills on proper sampling methods, sample treatment and preservation, subsequent analyses, preparation and presentation of analytical data for informed management decisions.
- Performed routine analyses, preparation of stock solutions, machine calibrations and laboratory housekeeping activities.
- Improved accuracy, computation and interpersonal skills.
- Teamed up with three senior Geochemists and successfully conducted comprehensive analysis on Olkaria II Geothermal production wells and generated analytical data for carbon credit.

May 2008- 2009: Chemistry & Physics teacher at Enkinda Secondary School in Nyamira County.

- Vastly interacted with young learners with rich divergent ideas, imparted them with scientific knowledge and problem solving skills, a strong positive attitude towards new challenges through self-confidence and hard-work.
- Developed my written and spoken communication skills as well as timely completion of tasks.

SEMINARS AND TRAININGS

- 12th Oct 2017: Attended training on Paints, Solvents and Coil Coating Technology held at Kansai Plascon
 Ltd (formerly Sadolin Paints), presided over by Mr. Vishal Hakim Technical Sales Manager.
- 10th 14th July 2017: Attended an ISO 9001:2015 & ISO 14001:2015 TRANSITION TRAINING held at Kaluworks Ltd (Mariakani), conducted by Bureau Veritas (ISO certification body).
- 19th 21st June 2017: Attended training on Paint Application technology held at Kaluworks Ltd (Mariakani) and presided over by Mr. Benjamin Ogwagwa Research & Development Manager at Monopol Colors Ltd (MCEA).
- 14th May 2015: Attended a Workshop on Roofing Materials Standards and information for Manufacturers, Importers and Construction Companies held at Bamburi Beach Hotel, Mombasa Facilitated by Kenya Bureau of Standards (KEBs), KIE Ltd and Manufacturers of Roofing Systems (Space & Style Ltd, Mabati Rolling Mills Ltd, Kaluworks Ltd & Maisha Mabati Mills Ltd).
- **16TH Nov 2012**: attended an academic building forum on the theme; **THE ROLE OF THE YOUTHS AND THE ASPIRATIONS OF VISION 2030** presided by Mr. Mugo Kibati, then CEO of Kenya vision 2030.
- **June, 2012**: participated in a Capacity building field training on proper sampling and analysis techniques organized by KenGen Ltd and presided by Mr. Daad, a Senior geochemist from Iceland.
- **28th Jan 2012**: Attended a seminar on Analytical Instrumentation, Laboratory Safety And Fire Management held at Kenyatta University, Presided over by Mr. Mwei Kennedy Chemical Analyst at Simba Cement.
- **23**rd **and 24**th **Oct 2011**: Actively participated in life saving skills training and drill held at Kenyatta University. The following modules were covered:

Basic First Aid, Fire Fighting Skills, Peace Building And Emergency Scene Management.

6th Mar, 2010: Attended a students' Seminar on APPRECIATING CHEMISTRY IN THIS DYNAMIC AND COMPETITIVE WORLD presided by Dr. Karanja Thiong'o, Lecturer and Director of Kenyatta University Industrial Linkages.

INTERESTS

Keen to apply both life and professional skills while keeping up with modern technology to provide robust solutions to challenges confronting the contemporary world.

CLUBS AND SOCIETIES

- Kenyatta University Society of Industrial and Analytical Chemists (KUSIAC).
- Kenyatta University Green Chemistry Club (KUGCC).
- Borabu constituency Kenyatta University Students Association (BOCKUSA).
- High school Science and Technology Empowerment Programme (HSTEP) KU Chapter.
- Kenyatta University Catholic Church (KUCC).
- Kenyatta University Red Cross Society.

HOBBIES

- Traveling and making friends.
- Playing basketball and table tennis.
- Internet browsing and watching scientific documentaries.

REFEREES:

Ms Winnie Ngumi, 1.

Chief Executive Officer.

Space and Style Ltd,

P.O Box 27764-00506,

Nairobi.

Phone: 0723177222

Email: winnie@spaceandstyle.co.ke

2. Dr. Oyoo Daniel,

Senior Lecturer and Associate Dean School Of Eng.

Kenyatta University,

P.O Box 43844-00100,

Nairobi.

Phone: **0721942475**

Email: danoyoo@hotmail.com

3. Ms. Ann Nungari,

Senior Geochemist,

Kenya Electricity Generating Company Ltd,

Olkaria Geothermal Project,

P.O Box 785, Naivasha. Phone: 0724510869.

4. Ms Salome Kago,

Quality Assurance Manager

Kaluworks Ltd.

P.O Box 89128, Mombasa

Phone: 0722471066

Email: salomekago@gmail.com